<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.3.2">Jekyll</generator><link href="http://localhost:4000/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="http://localhost:4000/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" hreflang="en" /><updated>2024-11-10T21:07:59+01:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/feed.xml</id><title type="html">Simone Giancola’s webpage</title><subtitle>MS Data Science @Bocconi
</subtitle><entry><title type="html">Useful Resources for Research</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/blog/2024/useful-resources-for-research/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Useful Resources for Research" /><published>2024-04-24T10:01:00+02:00</published><updated>2024-04-24T10:01:00+02:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/blog/2024/useful-resources-for-research</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/blog/2024/useful-resources-for-research/"><![CDATA[<p>I always like to find tools that can help me. Here is a non-exhaustive list of things I found around for research.</p>

<!-- There are websites, packages, and a doc I wrote down to summarize many useful tips about writing research works, which made me recently realize that most of my older documents are wrong 😕. Whatever, now I know, we are made for mistakes.  -->

<!-- I am also adding my new LaTeX template. It is basically a personalization of a very standard one, included below. -->

<p>Any suggestion is welcome!</p>

<ul>
  <li><a href="https://www.zotero.org/">Zotero</a> and its Chrome extension;</li>
  <li><a href="https://obsidian.md/">Obsidian</a> as main platform;</li>
  <li><a href="https://apps.ankiweb.net/">Anki</a> for spaced repetition memory;</li>
  <li><a href="https://www.scholar-inbox.com/">Scholar inbox</a>;</li>
  <li><a href="https://arxivist.com/">ArXivist</a>;</li>
  <li><a href="https://github.com/google-research/arxiv-latex-cleaner">arxiv-latex-cleaner</a> package;</li>
  <li><a href="https://notebooklm.google/">NotebookLM</a> now very simple but hoepfully will get better;</li>
  <li><a href="https://marketplace.visualstudio.com/items?itemName=valentjn.vscode-ltex">LTeX</a> extension for VSCode</li>
  <li>the <a href="https://www.miede.de/">Classic Thesis</a> LaTeX template;</li>
  <li>my personal adaptation on <a href="https://www.overleaf.com/read/gtpgcvpfyqkx#c8fbbf">Overleaf</a> or <a href="https://github.com/simonegiancola09/adapted_classic_thesis/tree/main">GitHub</a>;</li>
  <li>a <a href="http://simonegiancola09.github.io/assets/pdf/writing_a_paper.pdf">doc</a> summarizing in bullet points how to write a paper from the references therein.</li>
</ul>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="theory" /><category term="research" /><category term="goodstuff" /><category term="formal" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Links, documents, packages I found around.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">A Faraway Continent</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/blog/2024/a-faraway-continent/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="A Faraway Continent" /><published>2024-04-18T23:01:00+02:00</published><updated>2024-04-18T23:01:00+02:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/blog/2024/a-faraway-continent</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/blog/2024/a-faraway-continent/"><![CDATA[<p>I am writing this while being almost finished with my experience in Saudi Arabia. Here, I wish to recollect thoughts about my perspective on the country, and my choice to be there for three months. First, I hope I will not make it sound like the classic review of these places. The reason for me to go to Saudi Arabia was twofold: I wished to gain research experience, and I wanted to do so in a field that was distant from my previous attempts. This is because I am still very junior and do not want to crystallise into one single topic from the beginning. For this reason, I am very happy of how it turned out to be.</p>

<p>Moving on to the actual place, the project of KAUST is amazing. Never anywhere in the world there is a city built for the purpose of hosting a university. The effort to do so is remarkable, and has to be recognised. I felt great here, and would do this again anytime. The quality of research is even more enhanced by the fact that here research is valued, a lot.</p>

<p>Moving to the human side, differences do not create boundaries, and challenges are interesting, so when going to another continent, it is always stimulating, just differently. Obviously, moving to the US one will clash with some things, and moving to the Middle East some others will appear. Nevertheless, the effect is the same: growing as a human being and strengthening personality. I have learned so much from being here, especially in terms of how prejudice kills interactions, and often word of mouth does not relate with actual reality (in the sense of: you never know until you try). I come back to my home country with a different view on the struggles that the people of Saudi Arabia have, as well as their strengths. Here, you can smell that there is an identity, that goes well beyond the concept of country, and I feel like it is very suggestive to experience it live. In the desert, in the cities, in the shops, these people leave a mark. On the personal side, especially the last month has not been easy for me. The stress of wanting to do research, the judgment from admission processes, and the deadlines came all together. Thankfully, I can say that without a doubt this trying period made me learn a lot.</p>

<p>Thank you KAUST, and thank you Saudi Arabia, I have never felt so welcomed by the local people, and will always cherish this memory with me. I hope that people from far away in Europe will understand this, and come visit you, enhancing the globalisation that you so much wish to have.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="nontheory" /><category term="life" /><category term="thoughts" /><category term="memories" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[A hard time, beauty is in the differences. Saudi is different.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">When Stuck in an Airport</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/blog/2024/when-stuck-in-airport/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="When Stuck in an Airport" /><published>2024-04-12T23:01:00+02:00</published><updated>2024-04-12T23:01:00+02:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/blog/2024/when-stuck-in-airport</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/blog/2024/when-stuck-in-airport/"><![CDATA[<p>I am in between flights. Without noticing, I bought quite a strange ticket, through a rather risky procedure. In simple words: the connection is not official, and the seller decided to give me a 10 hrs overlay to avoid complaints. Therefore, I am currently in Istanbul, with very bad internet (despite the airport claiming to be very good at this, according to some suspicious ranking, as always).</p>

<p>In addition to this, I feel very tired, and have no energy whatsoever to think about Mathematics. Perhaps, this is also due to the fact that last week I graduated, and still carry on with me a very heavy luggage packed with thoughts and emotions. <br />
By no means I am a person that likes to make speeches about what I think; yet often it happens that I feel like I need to write down somewhere that whatever you see here is certainly not due to my inner strength. Indeed, I am fortunate enough to be surrounded by wonderful people that support me everyday consistently. While I did want to acknowledge this officially in my thesis, strange page-limit rules prevented me from doing so fully. The space was just enough to mention family and academic connections, leaving me no option but to postpone friends. <br />
To this day, I still feel bad for this, and want to make up for it. Since webpages are infinite, and I notably always joke about my friends not reading this loser blog, I will write down some thoughts that will probably get lost in the bits of the net. I do love this little fact, since it allows me not to show off anything, but still recognise that nothing was done by me as a single human being. 
<br />
From this moment onwards, I will switch to Italian for obvious reasons.</p>

<p>Per prima cosa, mi sento di dovere vivamente ringraziare Marta, Vittorio, Chiara, e Gianluca. Il fatto che siate venuti alle 7:45 di mattina alla laurea di un poveretto non è altro che l’ennesima dimostrazione che mi avete apprezzato, oltre ogni possibile difetto a incomprensione. <br />
Chiara e Marta: siete le sorelle che non ho mai avuto, e tanto desiderato. Mi avete preso col cucchiaino in molti casi, e fatto sempre sentire accolto e compreso. Non ho veramente parole, spero che la vita per voi sia fantastica, e di farne parte. Ogni giorno che sono via, vi penso. <br />
Gianluca e Vittorio, grazie al rugby vi ho conosciuto, e ho trovato due persone tanto diverse quanto speciali. La distanza e l’assenza non cambieranno mai il fatto che per un periodo di adolescenza facevamo una cosa tanto matta quanto divertente e legante. Col tempo, crescendo, ci siamo anche ritrovati in tanti altri interessi, e sono fiero di potere divertirmi con voi, sacrificando impegni e scadenze. Vittorio, la tua personalità è incredibile, non cambiare mai. Gianluca, tra i mille programmi e le mille discussioni, da persone diverse ci siamo allineati su tantissimi aspetti. Uno dei miei desideri più grandi è che quei progetti vadano avanti, e che più gente capisca che dietro ci sono persone speciali. Questo vale anche per gli altri ragazzi in questo post, che sono partiti da feste a caso su un laghetto sconosciuto e finora si stanno divertendo, anche tanto. \ 
Il viaggio a Santa Margherita, e la fantastica settimana in Sardegna, che includono tutti e 4 voi, sono tuttora parte dei miei pensieri.</p>

<p>Continuando, sono felicissimo di avere costruito un rapporto decennale con i tre amici di vecchia data: Lorenzo R., Stefano e Lorenzo C. Tutti, in un modo o nell’altro, sono partiti e hanno cambiato il modo in cui ci relazioniamo, senza mai però perdere un legame che pare andare oltre molti schemi. \ 
Lorenzo, sei forse la persona che conosco da più tempo, dalle elementari, alle medie insieme, vagando per un doposcuola fatto di debosciati e tante risate. Mi criticavi per il mio svizzerame e poi ti sei trasferito te. Sono sempre, non visibilmente, emozionato a riaggiornarmi con le tue storie. <br />
Stefano, finalmente ti sei smosso andando via, sono felicissimo per te. Sei sempre stato, nonostante arrivassi 30 minuti in ritardo, e io ti aspettavo sotto il sole, l’amico più caro che abbia. <br />
Infine, Lorenzo. Non ho ancora idea di come una tua partenza per Roma alle medie non abbia scalfito il nostro rapporto. Sorrido sempre ripensando al fatto che ci siamo conosciuti con il Catechismo, cosa che è tutto un programma contando che non mettiamo piede in chiesa da anni. In un modo o nell’altro, ci siamo cercati e incontrati molto più di tanta gente che vive nella mia stessa città, e penso sia una cosa bellissima. 
Mai dimenticherò l’infinita di nullafacenza di quei giorni a San Benedetto, o delle estati passate a Milano.</p>

<p>Muovendosi su cose meno vintage, negli ultimi anni ho avuto modo di conoscere molte persone che si sono rivelate essere speciali. Non seguirò un ordine preciso, e comunque tanto nessuno leggerà queste frasi, quindi mi posso permettere di non pensare troppo. <br />
Cari Mattia, Lorenzo S. e Luca. Tra oratorio e rugby ci siamo conosciuti, ma non ho una idea precisa di come ci siamo veramente avvicinati. La vostra capacità di esternalizzare pensieri e emozioni mi stupisce sempre, e mi attrae verso le vostre vicende, che ormai in parte sono anche le mie. Nonostante i continui battibecchi, sapete che vi apprezzo e ammiro, per quello che siete. Il legame che avete vi rende unici. <br />
Matilde, Camilla e Antonella, una mia visita a san Benedetto ci ha fatto incontrare, in modo rocambolesco e strano. Ricordo ancora che solo molti mesi dopo ci siamo propriamente scambiati i numeri, nonostante fossimo già legati. Per Antonella, ho sempre visto con invidia la tua forte personalità. Penso che questa cosa ti differenzi tantissimo dalla massa. Matilde, sei strana, espressiva, permalosa, tutto in termini che, per quanto mi riguarda, fortificano. Per finire, Camilla, da monosillabi alle parole crociate siamo finiti a discutere di qualsiasi cosa, e questo dice tanto, di come le persone cambino e crescano col tempo.</p>

<p>Negli anni, sono stato anche a forte contatto con la divertente sofferenza dello studio, che ha incluso tante delle persone qua sopra. Grazie a luoghi di incontro, sono stato fortunatissimo a imbattermi in Viola e Francesca. Cara Viola, la tua forza è la spontaneità e il tuo modo originale di trovare sempre interesse nelle cose, con un pizzico di invidia che forse ti manda avanti. Per me sei sempre stata fortissima. Francesca, ci siamo sempre trovati, in pensieri, musica, ideali. Mi appoggio spesso a te per parlare di tante cose: da Frah Quintale ai diritti delle persone più deboli; mi sento sempre interessato a quello che pensi a riguardo. Ancora ricordo i dubbi agli inizi dell’università, e mi fa impazzire pensare a quanto sia cambiato da allora, ormai mi appoggio io a te.  <br />
Allo stesso tempo, e questo vale per te e Viola ma anche per gli altri: fare le parole crociate sotto il sole con voi non batterà mai nessuna altra attività di svago. In un certo universo, vorrei stare per sempre sotto quei gazebo marciti, o sui lettini di qualche lido cafone nell’adriatico, con le vecchie che fanno spinning a mezz’acqua.</p>

<p>Giulio, Carlos e Francesco. Già ci conoscevamo, di vista e di giovane imbecillità. Vi ho riscoperto, come se foste persone diverse. Il vostro modo di essere amici è genuino e difficile da vedere altrove. Come vi ho già detto altre volte, piangere dal ridere non succede fuori dall’Italia; in stati che non sono casa tua. Mentre questo potrebbe essere generico, la verità è che ogni volta che lo dico o lo penso, mi vengono in mente i momenti in quel gazebo del Rapsody. Poi non posso togliermi dalla testa il pensiero, e mi rimane come un parassita per ore, dentro, a scavare nelle emozioni.</p>

<p>Arrivati a questo punto, posso solo destrutturare i ringraziamenti al di fuori dei gruppi, perchè non riesco molto ad associare persone a esperienze passate propriamente insieme, se non in parte. <br />
Federico, abbiamo avuto un momento di discussione molto forte, ma sono certo, e lo vedo già ora, che ci stiamo riavvicinando. Ti ho incontrato e rincontrato tante volte, e sei sempre originale, fuori dalla norma. Forse per questo ci siamo sempre sentiti accomunati nei nostri spigoli. <br />
Sofia, ti ho conosciuto tramite tua sorella, tra cene bellissime che urlavano svago, feste, e un viaggio in Sardegna. Di questo, sono felicissimo, e non nascondo che sia anche perchè in tanti modi siamo contrari, e io ho sempre invidiato gli artisti. La tua energia mi spiazza. <br />
Edoardo e Gabriele, so che col tempo e gli impegni ci siamo persi di vista, e so che questo sia senza volontà. Il vortice della vita ci ha portato un po’ più lontano. Nonostante ciò, quello che abbiamo condiviso in quei campi inguardabili di Domenica, svegliandosi la mattina e buttando tutto il giorno, mi ha sempre riempito l’anima. Siete e sarete dei grandi amici sempre.</p>

<p>Muovendosi sulle persone che ho conosciuto veramente recentemente, per quanto ormai siano già sei bellissimi anni, non posso che dedicare un enorme pensiero ai ragazzi della triennale. Nunzio, sei incredibile, sono fierissimo del tuo risultato, tanto sudato e desiderato. Come al solito, ci vedremo in qualche parte del mondo. Andrea, mi hai sempre accolto, nei tuoi vari spostamenti, prendendo una scimmia a casa tua. Non hai idea di quanto mi dispiacesse per come è andata a Parigi, dove ti trovavi bene, ma sono certo che Zurigo, o un altro posto, sarà la tua nuova casa. Roberto, ti sto sempre addosso, ma sai che ti ammiro, tantissimo. Alla fine, sei quello che spinge più forte di tutti e lo sappiamo bene.</p>

<p>Per chiunque altro che sia finito nella mia strada, grazie. Sia immediatamente che in ritardo, ho sempre imparato una lezione.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="nontheory" /><category term="life" /><category term="thoughts" /><category term="memories" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Acknowledgements, act II]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">The (unexpected) Parisian Experience</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/blog/2023/france-wrap-up/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The (unexpected) Parisian Experience" /><published>2023-12-26T22:01:00+01:00</published><updated>2023-12-26T22:01:00+01:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/blog/2023/france-wrap-up</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/blog/2023/france-wrap-up/"><![CDATA[<p>I have recently finished my wonderful stay at École Normale Supérieure. It has been a busy three months, of which I am very grateful. The city is a beautiful mess, and literally never sleeps. People on the undergound grind their whole trip to work at any time of the day, as I did. On the relax side, the <strong>Parisien</strong> know well when to rest. It looks like everyone is aware of the toll that the city places upon its citizens, something that I did not really understand the first month.</p>

<p>Despite this, I have been supported by wonderful people, in what probably is <strong>The</strong> institution for research. Without exxageration, my corridor held a portion of the best researchers in the field, as well as lots of young promising colleagues, always available to discuss and help. I can only thank everyone for their time and willingness to make me grow.</p>

<p>On a very important aspect to remark, France, and especially Paris, are some of the very rare places where researchers are not only respected but protected. This is very noticeable on many aspects, from job security to freedom of research. Despite the sweet beaurocracy very akin to the Italian style, these guys do know how to keep a clever person (like the ones I was with) thrive. Their love extends so much that the most important names in science make their way to be engraved in the Eiffel Tower, which is something that amazes me to this day. Long live to this, France is a place of freedom and self-expression! I can only respect this way of thinking.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="nontheory" /><category term="research" /><category term="life" /><category term="europe" /><category term="opinions" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[A wrap-up of my three months in France]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Things I Am Grateful For</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/blog/2023/things-i-am-grateful-for/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Things I Am Grateful For" /><published>2023-10-01T00:00:00+02:00</published><updated>2023-10-01T00:00:00+02:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/blog/2023/things-i-am-grateful-for</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/blog/2023/things-i-am-grateful-for/"><![CDATA[<p>Things I am grateful for</p>

<hr />
<p>layout: post
title:  What I Am Grateful for
date: 2023-09-31 21:01:00
Description: Discussing some aspects of life that I sometimes forget to acknowledge
tags: thoughts informal goodthings
categories: nontheory
—</p>

<p>After a very happy period in Austria, and a month spent back at home, I am in the position to assess my life situation in a way that I hardly could have had years ago. I have seldom been the type of person that recognizes aspects of life that are not for granted, so I will take this moment and this post to collect many things I should try not to forget. Maybe it will be helpful in the hard times.</p>
<h3 id="one-important-remark">One important remark</h3>
<p>This discussion will almost certainly be under continuous updates.</p>

<h2 id="the-humans">The humans</h2>
<p>First of all, I am grateful to my family. My parents have always supported me, pushing me forward without ever doubting what I wanted to do. My brother: we have grown together and shared so much across the years, I cannot even describe with words what I think about the bond we have. My grandparents, who have raised me since I was little with so much love, all for nothing in return. I am grateful to each and every eccentric, strange and lovely member of my family that has even partially been part of me growing up. As a matter of fact, I sometimes feel even closer to those that have always been hours away from my hometown.</p>

<p>Secondly, I am very proud of being able to say that I met a LOT of people that have been fundamental over the years. Both in Italy and abroad. I really love having many friends, texting them, asking them about their life, discussing stupid and clever ideas. Among the many, each one has a peculiar trait that makes the relationship worth it. I am super happy that everyone is struggling daily with their lives and willing to share some of it with me, and feel very fortunate that they can bear my sometimes very daunting personality. I do wish the best for them. I know I will want to pursue paths that will take me far away from most (if not all of them), but they will always be in my heart.</p>

<h2 id="the-things">The things</h2>
<p>I feel very fortunate to have visited around TODO countries. Of these, I lived in more than 4, worked in more than 3. Being 24 years old, this is very peculiar, especially since it was never because of my parents’ professional career. I have always wanted to travel, and got offered to on many occasions, for which I was sometimes (most of) financially supported. This is clearly not an opportunity that everyone has, and I do think it is something I am extremely thankful for. Travelling is one of the activities that makes you grow up faster, and I have certainly been exposed to it. 
I have also had the sheer luck of finding something I like and being able to pursue it. This is by no means common and must be recognized. Being able to reason about questions as a job is a privilege that is not given to many, and I work each day to prove my worth in this matter, that is very long to come (if ever). And this is just the tip of the iceberg of a collection of good events that led me to be able to get here. Many life stages have been fundamental and without them I would not be in this situation. 
I do love the fact that these same things in life have brought numerous side effects, not only related to “job life”. The constant stimulus and the wish for being exposed to many different contexts have brought me to greatly enjoy music, art, cinema, poetry, and many other activities that do not overlap a lot with what I try to do day-to-day. Despite this, I have always had great admiration for those that are able to perform them, and am always on the look for new things to listen, watch, contemplate or learn about. Now and always,I am grateful to be allowed to pursue what I like, 99% of the time. Knowing that this is very rare, it is probably the luckiest part of my everyday life.</p>

<h2 id="south">South</h2>
<p>On a side note, I am strangely super proud of having visited most of the southern part of Italy. Despite the large critics brought forward, the south is unbeatable. The power of the people, the strong culture and the beauty truly do not deserve the treatment it has always received. I wish Italy will once be a place where the south has blossomed.</p>
<h3 id="a-quick-flow-of-thought-rant">A quick “flow of thought” rant</h3>
<p>However, if I had to think straight, this is not going to happen. I will forever be left thinking about lower Italy’s broken beauty: Sicilia, Puglia, Campania, Sardinia (not proper south), and the most underrated Calabria. Even only the smell of their lands is impossible to find anywhere else. 
Unfortunately, the way in which politics, people and societal dynamics are not making their situation better is appalling. If I could choose, I would 100% live in the south. As a matter of fact, I believe that most Italians unreasonably think that life in the north is better, while it is actually not, at all. Maybe this deserves more context, and will be discussed on a different occasion. Long live to the south!!!</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Things I am grateful for]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">My 2 cents on Wien, IST and doing Research</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/blog/2023/austria-wrap-up/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="My 2 cents on Wien, IST and doing Research" /><published>2023-08-27T23:01:00+02:00</published><updated>2023-08-27T23:01:00+02:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/blog/2023/austria-wrap-up</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/blog/2023/austria-wrap-up/"><![CDATA[<p>Sadly, my period in Austria has come to an end. The internship was a summer gig and in October I will join another lab.</p>

<p>Wien is a wonderful place. I do not think I have lived in enought cities to develop a wise judgement, but I can safely say it has been the best one so far. In few words: it works. It’s safe, public transport is highly encouraged, life is easy and not as expensive as Milan for example. People never bother you and everyone is respectful. It’s not perfect, but nobody wants it. I highly recommend a visit.</p>

<p>In the summer (I was told the winter is kind of harder), you literally breathe life. People are out, things happen, there is in general a strong drive to enjoy what is thrown on the table. What struck me the most is the underground. Given that all citizens use it, it is some kind of open air view of the life of each resident. A TV-show with people falling in love and breaking up, happiness and sadness, very very nice. I really enjoyed this bit of my stay: where there is emotions there is wellness and humanity over all, believe it or not.</p>

<p>Getting to my job at the Institute of Science and Technology Austria (in short ISTA), it has been wonderful. A very nice place, awesome people, and a solid expansion project. I am not an expert of research environments, but I could feel that there is some long-term project in the institution that goes well beyond my stay or everyone else’s. 
I have deeply enjoyed challenging myself in conducting research, and am now more than ever convinced to pursue a research career. This was never in doubt, but somehow every experience gives me more and more motivation.</p>

<p>Thank you IST, Thank you to the organizers of the internship. Thank you Marco, you have been a great supervisor, and your topics of research are very cool. Thank you to the whole group for being nice, for hosting me and teaching me every day something new. I will do my best to see you again sometime somewhere.</p>

<p>To anyone reading this, if you have the opportunity to spend some time in Wien or do research at IST, please go!</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="nontheory" /><category term="research" /><category term="life" /><category term="europe" /><category term="opinions" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[A Wrap-up of my Three Months in Austria]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">A List of Lists of Interesting Things</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/blog/2023/list-of-interesting-things/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="A List of Lists of Interesting Things" /><published>2023-07-23T23:01:00+02:00</published><updated>2023-07-23T23:01:00+02:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/blog/2023/list-of-interesting-things</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/blog/2023/list-of-interesting-things/"><![CDATA[<p>A list of things that I enjoyed throughout the years.</p>

<p><strong>Books</strong></p>

<p>I have a <a href="https://www.goodreads.com/user/show/180790738-simone-maria">goodreads account</a>, you can check all my readings there!</p>

<p><strong>Cool Links</strong></p>
<ul>
  <li><a href="https://www.prisonmathproject.org/">Prison Mathematics Project</a></li>
  <li><a href="https://mathwithbaddrawings.com/">Math with bad drawings</a></li>
</ul>

<p><strong>Sculptors</strong></p>
<ul>
  <li>Jago</li>
  <li>Daniel Arsham</li>
  <li>Paolo Nicolai</li>
  <li>Fabio Viale</li>
  <li>Leo Caillard</li>
  <li>Filippo Nicolini</li>
  <li>Francesco Filiberto Tonnarelli</li>
  <li>Federico Benedetti</li>
  <li>Bruno Cesar Catalano</li>
  <li>Massimiliano Pelletti</li>
</ul>

<p><strong>Photographers</strong></p>
<ul>
  <li>Merrick Morton</li>
  <li>George Steinmetz</li>
  <li>Michael Yamasita</li>
  <li>Steve McCurry</li>
  <li>Joel Sartore</li>
  <li>Aaron Huey</li>
  <li>Robin Hammond</li>
  <li>Brent Stirton</li>
  <li>Babak Tafreshi</li>
  <li>Gabriele Galimberti</li>
  <li>Pedro McBride</li>
  <li>Marshall Cody</li>
  <li>Shaaz Jung</li>
  <li>Paul Nicklen</li>
  <li>Sam Alexander Gregg</li>
  <li>Michael Christopher Brown</li>
  <li>Herbert van der Beek</li>
  <li>Lenny J. Ruiz</li>
  <li>Suitcase Joe</li>
  <li>Sam Youkilis</li>
  <li>Antonio Faccilongo</li>
  <li>Alessandro Cinque</li>
  <li>Michele Iacobini</li>
  <li>Leandro Colantoni</li>
  <li>Carmine Romano</li>
  <li>Niall McDiarmind</li>
  <li>Robbie McIntosh</li>
  <li>Martin Schoeller</li>
  <li>David Alan Harvey</li>
  <li>Bonus for the Italians: the collections “Archivio Balneare” and “Pictures from Italian Profiles” are worth checking out.</li>
</ul>

<p><strong>Contemporary Artists</strong></p>
<ul>
  <li>Alice Pasquini</li>
  <li>Shawn Coss</li>
  <li>Bordalo II</li>
  <li>Sean Yoro</li>
  <li>Iskander Utebayev</li>
  <li>Butcher Billy</li>
  <li>Guillermo Lorca Garcìa</li>
  <li>Omar Hassan</li>
  <li>Simone Bianchi</li>
  <li>Alex Juice</li>
  <li>Will Conrad</li>
  <li>Refik Anadol</li>
  <li>Filippo Giusti</li>
  <li>Roberto Ferri</li>
  <li>Maxim Zhestkov</li>
  <li>Fabrizio Plessi</li>
  <li>Sy Goldstein</li>
  <li>Nathan Stockman</li>
  <li>Flavio Solo</li>
</ul>

<p><strong>Music Albums</strong></p>
<ul>
  <li>Unknown Pleasures, Joy Division, 1979</li>
  <li>Closer, Joy Division, 1980</li>
  <li>Disintegration, The Cure, 1989</li>
  <li>Violator, Depeche Mode, 1990</li>
  <li>Lucio Dalla, Lucio Dalla, 1979</li>
  <li>Dalla, Lucio Dalla, 1980</li>
  <li>The Smiths, The Smiths, 1984</li>
  <li>Everybody Else Is Doing It, So Why Can’t We?, The Cranberries, 1993</li>
  <li>No Need To Argue, The Cranberries, 1994</li>
  <li>Recovery, Eminem, 2010</li>
  <li>The Slim Shady LP, Eminem, 1999</li>
  <li>One More Light, Linkin Park, 2017</li>
  <li>Meteora, Linkin Park, 2003</li>
  <li>Low-Life, New Order, 1985</li>
  <li>Substance, New Order, 1987</li>
  <li>La voglia la pazzia l’incoscienza l’allegria, Ornella Vanoni - Toquinho - Vinícius de Moraes, 1976</li>
  <li>Relax, Calcutta, 2023</li>
</ul>

<p><strong>Podcasts</strong></p>
<ul>
  <li>24 mattino, Radio 24</li>
  <li>Rassegna stampa, Radio 24</li>
  <li>La Zanzara, Radio 24</li>
  <li>Congo, Una Storia Sbagliata; Paolo Colombo</li>
  <li>Io Ero il Milanese; Mauro Pescio</li>
  <li>Lo Stato Parallelo; Gherardo Colombo</li>
  <li>Indagini; Stefano Nazzi</li>
  <li>Veleno; Pablo Trincia</li>
  <li>Mitologia: le Meravigliose Storie del Mondo Antico; Alessandro Gelain</li>
  <li>L’isola che non c’era; Marco Maisano</li>
  <li>La vita dopo, il caso Luca Delfino; Pietro Adami e Simone Gorla</li>
  <li>Dove nessuno guarda; Pablo Trincia</li>
  <li>Disobbedisco, Sibilla Barbieri, L’ultimo viaggio verso la Libertà; Valentina Petrini</li>
  <li>Ti scorderai di me; Sergio Ramazzotti e Giovanni Savarese</li>
  <li>L’inverno demografico - Cosa c’è da sapere; Mauro Meazza, Michela Finzio</li>
  <li>Io sono Libero; Alessandro Milan</li>
  <li>Il gioco del Mostro; Giulia Bianconi</li>
  <li>Il dito di Dio; Pablo Trincia</li>
  <li>A domani; Nicolò Agliardi</li>
  <li>Questo è Messina Denaro; Antonio Iovane, Lirio Abbate</li>
  <li>Il mostro di Firenze, la via dell’acqua; Luca Ward</li>
  <li>Benno - L’Oscurità su Bolzano; Lapo de Carlo, Noemi Zago, Stefano Dargenio</li>
  <li>Come una marea - Il caso Franco Mastrogiovanni; Francesca Zanni, Enrico Bergianti</li>
  <li>Sangue Loro, il ragazzo mandato a uccidere; Pablo Trincia</li>
  <li>Le ombre di via Poma; Giacomo Galanti</li>
  <li>Metanolo; Will media, Boats sound</li>
  <li>Rumore, il caso Federico Aldrovandi; Francesca Zanni, Enrico Bergianti</li>
  <li>E poi il silenzio; Pablo Trincia</li>
  <li>Almeno credo; Carlo De Ruggieri</li>
</ul>

<p><strong>Poets</strong></p>
<ul>
  <li>Guido Catalano</li>
  <li>Alda Merini</li>
  <li>Franco Arminio</li>
  <li>Pablo Neruda</li>
</ul>

<p><strong>Youtube Channels</strong></p>
<ul>
  <li>Soft White Underbelly, Mark Laita</li>
  <li>The Pillow</li>
  <li>The Happiness Project</li>
</ul>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="nontheory" /><category term="informal" /><category term="list" /><category term="music" /><category term="podcasts" /><category term="books" /><category term="photography" /><category term="art" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[A database of interesting material to read, listen, watch, contemplate]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">(ITA) La Teoria Cinecittà</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/blog/2023/la-teoria-cinecitta/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="(ITA) La Teoria Cinecittà" /><published>2023-04-05T23:01:00+02:00</published><updated>2023-04-05T23:01:00+02:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/blog/2023/la-teoria-cinecitta</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/blog/2023/la-teoria-cinecitta/"><![CDATA[<p>Roma ha sempre avuto un forte significato nella storia di chiunque sia nato in Italia. Senza differenze, lo ha anche nel mio caso. La trovo una città molto a misura di persona, nonostante le forti critiche che subisce. Al contrario, non sono convinto che una vita passata a Milano sia effettivamente desiderabile, anche per la mente più particolare.</p>

<p>In fin dei conti, stiamo confrontando inquinamento stress e tempo a dire poco penoso con bellezza, apoteosi della dolce vita e quieto vivere. Una prova tangibile di questo fatto è la stessa ambientazione di buona parte dei film italiani, di cui sono particolarmente appassionato. Raramente (per quanto riguarda quelli che apprezzo, mai) l’ambientazione, immaginaria o dichiarata che sia, ricorda quella del capoluogo lombardo. Nella maggior parte dei casi risulta invece essere uno spaccato di vita di cittadini della capitale.</p>

<p>La lista di film che segue raccoglie questo significato. Raccoglie l’Italia che tutti vorrebbero vivere, e le trame che tutti vorrebbero sperimentare. Non nascondo che alcuni siano forse troppo smielati a prima vista per il pubblico medio, ma spesso nascondono significati ben più profondi di quello che si possa pensare.</p>

<p>Data la memoria imperfetta, sarà una lista soggetta a continuo aggiustamento, così come sarà aggiornata con nuove pellicole che ancora mancano. La suddivisione è per attori / registi senza molta logica.</p>

<p><strong>Carlo Verdone</strong></p>
<ul>
  <li>Grande grosso e verdone</li>
  <li>Acqua e Sapone</li>
  <li>Maledetto il giorno che ti ho incontrato</li>
  <li>Manuale D’amore</li>
  <li>L’amore è Bello Finchè Dura</li>
  <li>Un Sacco Bello</li>
  <li>Viaggi di Nozze</li>
  <li>Bianco, Rosso e Verdone</li>
  <li>Io, Loro e Lara</li>
  <li>Il mio Miglior Nemico</li>
  <li>Sono pazzo di Iris Blond</li>
  <li>Compagni di Scuola</li>
</ul>

<p><strong>Massimo Troisi</strong></p>
<ul>
  <li>Il postino</li>
  <li>Non ci resta che piangere</li>
</ul>

<p><strong>Gabriele Muccino</strong></p>
<ul>
  <li>L’ultimo bacio</li>
  <li>Baciami Ancora</li>
  <li>Gli Anni più Belli</li>
  <li>A Casa Tutti Bene</li>
  <li>Come te Nessuno Mai</li>
  <li>Ricordati di me</li>
  <li>La Prima Cosa Bella</li>
</ul>

<p><strong>Paolo Sorrentino</strong></p>
<ul>
  <li>La grande Bellezza</li>
  <li>È stata la mano di dio</li>
</ul>

<p><strong>Edoardo Leo</strong></p>
<ul>
  <li>Era ora</li>
  <li>Perfetti Sconosciuti</li>
</ul>

<p><strong>Silvio Muccino</strong></p>
<ul>
  <li>Che ne sarà di noi</li>
</ul>

<p><strong>Riccardo Scamarcio</strong></p>
<ul>
  <li>Io che amo solo te</li>
  <li>Lo Spietato</li>
</ul>

<p><strong>Misti</strong></p>
<ul>
  <li>Lasciarsi un giorno a Roma</li>
  <li>Generazione Mille Euro</li>
  <li>Tutta la Vita Davanti</li>
  <li>Ovosodo</li>
  <li>Tutta Colpa di Freud</li>
  <li>Romanzo Criminale</li>
  <li>Il Ciclone</li>
</ul>

<p><strong>Menzione D’onore</strong>, per i film italiani di successo ma non ambientati propriamente in Italia.</p>
<ul>
  <li>Mediterraneo (Abatantuono, Bisio)</li>
  <li>La vita è Bella (Benigni)</li>
</ul>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="nontheory" /><category term="italian" /><category term="films" /><category term="informal" /><category term="list" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[una lista aggiornata di film e il cardine del mio ideale di Italia]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">On the Importance of Having a Mission</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/blog/2023/on-the-importance-of-having-a-mission/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="On the Importance of Having a Mission" /><published>2023-04-04T23:01:00+02:00</published><updated>2023-04-04T23:01:00+02:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/blog/2023/on-the-importance-of-having-a-mission</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/blog/2023/on-the-importance-of-having-a-mission/"><![CDATA[<p>The following is a confusing and very raw discussion about one of the most foundational aspects of my everyday life. In parallel, I will comment on
the last 12 months, since they have been the clearest example of <em>the importance of having a Mission</em>. Despite being 100% sure that I
am not a person able to give advice, you might pick up something in the end.</p>

<h3 id="why-such-a-corny-title">Why such a corny title?</h3>
<p>Being a huge hater of wrongfully formulated titles, I need to explain this in two or three sentences. For me, <em>having a Mission</em> means waking up with
a purpose. Such purpose is <em>purposely</em> not specified. It might be a career objective, a self-care target, a desire to provide for someone else (e.g. family).
Even a mix of these things is fine. Empirically, it just so happens that I can only focus on one, but maybe that is only my impression, or
self-infliction of a famous Italian belief that only women can do more than one thing at a time. Despite seeming itself corny as an explanation, if you actually 
think about it, you are only able to <strong>do</strong> something when it falls inside some big picture of yours where everything works out in the end.</p>

<p>Why would someone study, work, have a shower, cook, do anything at all if there is not some immediate and expected-long-term enjoyment?</p>

<p>It is also more or less true for myself that such Mission works best when designed to benefit someone else. While I do not expect this to hold in general, I will elaborate further in the paragraphs below.</p>

<h3 id="isnt-it-just-the-way-it-is">Isn’t it just the way it is?</h3>
<p>Well, yes and no. From the height of my 23 years of life (yes, I am consciously being ironic), I came to understand that focusing is something I need to impose to myself, rather than just independently going on. I have spent many years trying to follow my default desires, without structure, just to find out that planning is far more effective and helps you get what you want. Last year has been the uttermost achievement in this sense. I have found tranquility and happiness in pursuing a long-term dream that brought me to plenty short-term wonderful experiences.</p>

<h3 id="march-2022---march-2023">March 2022 - March 2023</h3>
<p>At the beginning of this period, I simply chose to follow an idea that seemed reasonable and fun enough. Despite not being my final desire for the future, which I guess for everyone is just to be happy and fulfilled, it is certainly what brings me the closest to it. After years of study, I decided to start the process of willingly attempting to pursue an academic career. This is not at all a finished task, and it might be never fulfilled, but it has been pivotal in these 365 days. There are two main reasons. First of all, it is something I enjoy, as much as very few other things in life. Secondly, it is an expression of willingness to do good for society. The side effects of this plan have been fantastic.</p>

<p>Gaslighted by it, I have thrived socially, as a person, and mentally, in contexts unrelated to performing scientific research. My belief is that it is due to the fact that I more or less found my way, and that the consciouness of it being useful for the community has in some sense let me be happier for myself.</p>

<h3 id="the-fil-rouge">The <em>fil rouge</em></h3>
<p>If you feel like your way was not found yet, what I observed in people that give the impression of being <em>on a Mission</em> (mine is just a copying mechanism), is that all of them are eventually based on love. Be it self-oriented, for the everyone else, for a specific community, in the end it is all the same. The
common thread is focusing on doing something good. The gains come later, almost instantly, and are often never forgotten.</p>

<p>Now more than ever, I see many peers struggling in this. My opinion is that it is better to focus on a stupid mission rather than ignoring the issue in its entirety. The main reason is that without an objective, you have no identity, and without an identity, you will lose yourself. Oftentimes, it happens that this elightenment must come from someone else in your life. In my case, this is true more than ever. I started understanding how to be happy when I found out that I must look further than below my nose, since people around me are the easiest example of how life can go on, especially when yours is not at all going.</p>

<h3 id="when-are-the-results-coming">When are the results coming?</h3>
<p>Aware that this is a topic impossible not to care about, my guess is <strong>instantly</strong>. Despite having set such a foggy and not at all straight objective, the path that I am following has lead to many side results, sometimes completely unrelated, that have kept me going, and will keep me going. I have enjoyed studying and getting good grades, but I also had the privilege of cultivating strong friendships along the way, finding an inner balance, and having probably the best fun of my life. Even though last year I wrote almost 1000 computer-typed and countless (approx. 4000) handwritten pages of mathematics, 
I somehow found more time to hang out, bond, have holidays, party, work, think. All of this is thanks to waking up with already half of the work done (i.e. knowing what to wish for). No agenda planning, no specific tasks, no pressure, just knocking at every door possibly linked to what I wanted to do.</p>

<h3 id="future">Future</h3>
<p>My guess is that I will go on, and just see what happens. There are expectations, but even if something will not work out, there is always love on the backline (again, not in the corny sense of the word), so I <strong>will</strong> be fine. A mission never dies, it just keeps on stimulating your self-development, and that is probably what makes it even better.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="nontheory" /><category term="thoughts" /><category term="informal" /><category term="goodthings" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[A wrap up of thoughts]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Rules of the game</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/blog/2023/rules-of-the-game/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Rules of the game" /><published>2023-04-01T23:01:00+02:00</published><updated>2023-04-01T23:01:00+02:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/blog/2023/rules-of-the-game</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/blog/2023/rules-of-the-game/"><![CDATA[<h2 id="some-boring-introduction">Some Boring introduction</h2>
<p>This is my first attempt at writing a blog. Despite being strange, and kind of old-fashioned, it might actually be fun so I thought of giving it a try.</p>

<p>I still do not know if this will be a fixed activity, or more influenced by randomness, and what I will talk about. Short term topics are likely to be a mix of Mathematics, music, films, and socially felt problems. My guess is that I will talk a bit about what I am studying at the moment, and occasionally use some posts to talk about non work related topics. The general aim is collecting thoughts to see what changes in years in terms of <em>writing</em>, <em>thinking</em> and <em>seeing</em>.</p>

<h2 id="content-delivery">Content Delivery</h2>
<p>Concerning non Science related subjects, I would like this to be a free area in which I can type down whatever comes to my mind. Respect will be always kept, but please keep in mind that as Twitter users state in their bio: “opinions are my own”.</p>

<p>I guarantee you that I will not be as hard as one of my favourite radio programs, “La Zanzara” on Radio24, but at the same time not as soft as national television. I feel like one of the most important things in life are discussion and developing ideas, and a blog looks like a perfect fit for both.</p>

<h2 id="language">Language</h2>

<p>The impression is that I am bad at writing in both English and Italian, the only two languages I known enough to even formulate more than 3 sentences. I might alternate between the two indefinitely, but will point out when a post is in my native language. It is hihgly likely that academic and life matters will be repsectively in English and Italian, with occasional crossover English posts when talking about international topics that are non technical.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="general" /><category term="metablogging" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Blog presentation]]></summary></entry></feed>